Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Business Documents, 1799-1809; 16 Linear feet
  - Business Papers, 1797-1805 (Box 71)
    This box includes 7 folders. Folder 1 has 6 sub-folders. These folders are comprised of bills for potash from 1797-1805. These bills predominantly have the name of the individual being sold to or the captain of the ship that the goods will be transported on. Most of the bills have a large amount of marginalia on them, which appear to be scratch notes by Hicks. Some of this writing states what ship the goods should be transported on, but most appear to be scratch notes and other random markings. The materials in this box were originally rolled into tight bundles, and therefore were sent to the conservation department for humidification and flattening. They have since been returned and are housed in folders in a document box.
  - Business Papers, Undated (Box 56)
    This box includes 5 folders of business papers. These papers are undated. They are not sorted into any specific order or topic, but appear to be comprised predominantly of bills, debits and credits, inventories, and similar documents.
  - Prices Current, 1799-1806 (Box 57)
    This box includes Prices Current from Liverpool, London, Ireland, France, Amsterdam, Rotterdam, Antwerp, Hamburg, Jamaica, Bilboa, Lisbon, St. Petersburg, and Genoa. Prices Current are a dated list of prices for goods commonly imported to or exported from the region. Some goods listed include wheat products, tobacco, staves, indigo, cocoa, coffee, and skins and furs. They are also known as Accounts Current. The folders are organized by location and then by year.
  - Invoices, 1791-1800 (Box 58)
    This box includes 9 folders of invoices from 1791 to 1800. These invoices are mostly for sundries and other smaller materials housed in trunks or bales. They include a list of goods, a description of the goods, and their prices. Goods include casks of oil, spermaceti candles, fabric, staves, dyes, and linens.
  - Invoices, 1801-1807 (Box 59)
    This box includes 5 folders of invoices from 1801-1807. These invoices are for goods shipped on multiple vessels, predominantly to Isaac Hicks. Most invoices include a list of goods, their descriptions, and prices. Some goods include cotton, tobacco, spermaceti candles, wool, linens, and assorted sundries.
  - Insurance Policies, 1791-1797 (Box 60)
    This box includes insurance policies taken out by Isaac Hicks on behalf of his clients. The insurance policies are both on ships and cargo for various amounts.
    Ships Mentioned: Hudson, Fryon, Friends Adventure, Good Intent, Sally, Pizarro, Thomas, Juno, Peggy, Hope, Fryal, Mary, Jenny, Polly, George, Nancy, Columbia, Franklin, Maria, Sally, George, Commerce, Hunter, Panne, Revolution, Ann, Pearl, Pomona, Albany, Suffolk, Elizabeth, Franklin, Oswego.
    Insurance Providers: Thomas Eddy, Robinson & Hartshorne, John Ferrers, John Knox, Knox & Briggs, Carlile Pollock & Edward Moore, Hugh Smith, Peter Griffen, Robert Alexander, Lawrence & Seton, Gasherie Brasher, John Henry, Winthrop & Lewis, David Reedy, Armstrong & Barnewall, New-York Insurance Company, United Insurance Company
  - Insurance Policies, 1798 (Box 61)
    Ships Mentioned: William, Mowhawk, Aurora, Betsy, Rachel, Janus, Franklin, Polly, Thomas, Howard, Nancy, Warren, Minerva, Mary Ann, Fortitude, Hudson, Trial, Leo, Joseph Hervey, Mars, Maria, Lydia, Juno, American Hero, Bedford, Wareham, Juliet, Caesar, John Jay, Active, Ruby, Olive Branch, Lyon
    Insurance Providers: John Bard Jr, New-York Insurance Company, United Insurance Company, Lessingwell & Pierpont
  - Insurance Policies, 1799 (Box 62)
    Ships Mentioned: Oswego, Olive Branch, Favorite, Lydia, Brutus, Nancy, Columbia, Lucretia, Hector, Ann, Renown, Juliet, Julianna, Linnet, Tourterelle, President, Hercules, Commerce, Washington, Tabitha, Bellona, Perseverance, Juno, Caroline, Rachel, Lucinda, Minerva, Hope, Union, Ruba, Eliza, Nymph, John, Thomas, Beaver, Mary, Sarah, Mercury, Cleopatra, Industry, Fame, Warren, Polly, Nixon, St. Andrew, Betsey, Diana, Fortitude, Brutus, Goliath, Hebe Lolling, Warren, Barclay, Charming Betsey.
    Insurance Providers: John Bard Jr., Bogert & Mansfield, United insurance Company, New-York Insurance Company, John Bard, Lessingwell & Pierpont
  - Insurance Policies, 1800-1801 (Box 63)
    Ships Mentioned: Oswego, Brutus, Debbe, Nancy, Mary, General Mercer, Olive Branch, Betsy, Maria, Manilla, Lucretia, Ajax, Sarah, Cleopatra, Happy Couple, Fortitude, Diana, Delight, Industry, Anna Maria, Willing Lass, Allegany, Patty, Fortitude, John, Venus, Ashasia, Hunter, Warren,, Industry, Elizabeth, Active, Osiris, Exchange, Lydia, Connecticut, Herkemer, Minerva, Peggy, Mowhawk, Brothers, Adventure, Beaver, Commerce, Jane, Abby, Columbia, Nixon, Ticonic
    Insurance Provider: John Bard, Bogert & Mansfield, United Insurance Company, John Bard Jr, Columbian Insurance Company, Bard & Barker, The Marine Insurance Company of New-York, Monson Hayt, Peter Griffen, New-York Insurance Company
  - Insurance Policies, 1802-1804 (Box 64)
    Ships Mentioned: Sarah, General Mercer, Sally, Allegany, Herkimer, Susan, Commerce, Warren, Columbia, Penman, William, Nixon, Exchange, Orient, Resource, Mars, Connecticut, Thames, Friends Adventure, Rufus, Thetis, Eliza Ann, Ceres, Diana, Connecticut, Nixon, Perseverance, General Mercer, Fortitude, Severn, Thames, Penman, Mentor, Guardian, Washington, Iris
    Insurance Providers: Bogert & Mansfield, Columbian Insurance Company, United Insurance Company, New-York Insurance Company, B.M. Mumford, The Marine Insurance Company of New-York, Commercial Insurance Company, James Seton & Co., Huntress.
  - Orders to Pay, 1795-1802 (Box 65)
    This box includes 13 folders include Orders to Pay. In these folders there are multiple types of orders. The first type of order requests Hicks to pay a specific amount of money to either the bearer or an individual, usually for a specific ship or set of goods. While most of these orders to pay are for money, there are some asking Hicks to provide goods owed. The second type of order is orders for others to pay Hicks. The third type of order is an order for insurance. These orders to pay are not in chronological order.
  - Orders to Pay, 1801-1804 (Box 66)
    This box includes 7 folders include Orders to Pay. These orders predominantly request Hicks to pay a specific amount of money to either the bearer or an individual, usually for a specific ship or set of goods. While most of these orders to pay are for money, there are some asking Hicks to provide goods owed. These orders to pay are not in chronological order.
  - Orders on Hicks to Pay, 1796-1801, Undated (Box 67)
    This box includes 8 folders include Orders to Pay. These orders request Hicks to pay a specific amount of money to either the bearer or an individual, usually for a specific ship or set of goods. While most of these orders to pay are for money, there are some asking Hicks to provide goods owed. Some of these orders are for immediate payment, while others resemble bills, asking Hicks to pay after a certain length of time has passed. These orders to pay are in chronological order by folder, but are not in chronological within the folder.
  - Orders on Hicks to Pay, 1802-1808 (Box 68)
    This box includes 6 folders include Orders to Pay. These orders request Hicks to pay a specific amount of money to either the bearer or an individual. While some of these orders are for immediate payment, most resemble bills, asking Hicks to pay after a certain length of time has passed. These orders to pay are in chronological order by folder, but are not in chronological within the folder.
  - Accounts, 1796-1800 (Box 69)
    This box includes 6 folders comprised of accounts current and debits and credits. While some of these accounts are based on accounts that Hicks had with specific individuals, most of the accounts are for individual ships. The accounts are a mix of long lists of goods shipped or materials used in the shipping process, and short lists of one or two different goods. There are also charges regarding tariffs and customs charges. Also included is a copy of a letter from Joseph Howard regarding a stay of execution for somebody that Hicks had sued.
  - Accounts, 1800-1807 (Box 70)
    This box includes 5 folders. They include orders to pay, accounts for individuals, accounts for ships (mostly lists), and accounts of sales, debits and credits. The accounts are not always for goods, but are sometimes for services provided (for example, inoculation for smallpox), insurance policies, notes of interests, and accounts current. Goods listed include cotton, tobacco, rice, soap, turpentine, "sundries", flaxseed, potash, and pearl ash.
  - Ships Papers: Thames, 1803-1804 (Box 72)
    This box includes four folders regarding two voyages of the ship Thames in 1803 and 1804. The documents include shipping orders, receipts, invoices, accounts current, reports & manifests, and bills. There are multiple documents in French and one document in Danish. One packet of letters includes a typewritten note that says "Ship Thames, 1803. First Voyage. Paddock Capt. Bills: Havre etc. Letters: Quenouille, Lanhcon, Henin & Spear. Note: Arthur Spear becomes an intimate friend of Judah Paddock goes to Verdun, is imprisoned by British. A petition of business men at Havre may get him released it is hoped." However, this packet of papers includes no letters or any information regarding why this note is with the specific packet of documents. It is unclear if this information comes from reading the correspondence in the collection or from another source.
  - Ships Papers: General Mercer, Venus, Undated (Box 73)
    This box includes 5 folders from the ships General Mercer and Venus. There are three folders for the ship General Mercer. Topics include bills, orders to pay, certification of measurement, inventories, disbursements, promises to pay, freight lists, and public instruments of protest. The public instruments of protest include details about the goings on of the ship, including goods shipped, the use of onboard materials, events on the ship, and weather events among other things. There are two folders for the ship Venus. Topics include freight lists, and many longer documents. There are multiple public instruments of protest. One document discusses shipping a load of planks on the ship and states "in case the boards or planks are washed away, he gets no freight." Another document is a certificate regarding the storage of boards on deck, stating the boards were in bad condition, so the buyer did not want to pay the agreed upon price, and there is a copy of an advertisement for the sale of the damaged goods.
  - Ships Papers: George Washington, West Point, Robert Bolton, 1805-1806 (Box 74)
    This box includes 8 folders from the ships George Washington, West Point, and Robert Bolton. There is one folder for the ship George Washington. It includes invoices for bundles, and debits and credits. The ship West Point has 3 folders. The folders include promises to pay, public notary notices, invoices, accounts sales, and many bills. There are multiple letters in French. Also included is a list of ships with captains, locations, destinations, cargo shipped, and date of departure. The ship Robert Bolton has four folders. They predominantly include bills and account materials.
  - Ships Papers, Undated (Box 75)
    This box contains 4 folders of undated materials. These materials primarily include lists of goods and writings discussing pipe staves and other goods, the ships they were sent on, and the cost of said goods. Also included are documents from the Port of Hamburg regarding goods shipped, and appear to be official documents and include a seal. They include certificates of duties paid, and certificates from the office of inspection at the port of Charleston.
    Some ships mentioned include Minerva, Happy Couple, Hawk, Peggy, Favourite, Jane, Nancy, Lydia
  - Ships Papers, 1798-1804 (Box 76)
    This box contains 8 folders of materials between 1798-1804. The documents regard how goods are shipped in good order and lists the goods shipped. Other documents include memorandums, lists of sales, accounts current, and documents from a public notary.
    Some ships mentioned include Minerva, Mary, Rover, Dispatch, Brutus, Polly, Diana
  - Ships Papers, 1801-1803 (Box 77)
    This box contains 5 folders of materials between 1801 and 1803. The documents are predominantly letters of lading, import certifications, accounts, and shipping certifications.
    The main ship mentioned is the General Mercer, though other ships are mentioned as well
  - Shipping Papers, 1795-1801, Undated. (Box 105)
    This box contains eleven folders of materials. The folders predominantly contain materials relating to the shipment of goods on specific ships.
  - Manifests, Freight Lists, 1798-1803 (Box 78)
    This box includes 3 folders of manifests and freight lists from 1798-1803. The folders include manifests, which include a list of goods shipped, by whom, and to whom. Some include the ports the goods are being shipped to and how many of each type of good has been shipped. Also included is a copy of an Act for the Government and Regulation of Seamen in the Merchants' Service.
    Ships mentioned include the General Mercer, Thomas, Herkimer, Diana, Perseverance, Nancy, Minerva
  - Protest Notes, 1794-1806 (Box 79)
    This folder includes 7 folders of materials from 1794-1806. The documents are in regards to payments such as orders to pay, promises to pay, and bills. There are lists of sales of parcels and sundries, lists of interests accrued, and accounts current. There are many letters written or signed by a notary public. Most letters are in regards to goods shipped and finances, while others are in regards to repairs and other topics.
  - Powers of Attorney, Auction Bills, Measures Reports & Bills, 1794-1808 (Box 80)
    This folder includes 5 folders regarding powers of attorney, auction bills, and measures reports & bills from 1794-1808. The first powers of attorney folder includes 9 pages of typewritten notes added to the collection at a later date. These notes include dated descriptions of the documents included in the folders. It is unclear if every document is noted in this typewritten note. The powers of attorney are predominantly for Isaac Hicks to take possession and responsibility for different ships. The auction bills are also labeled simply as sales. Some include lists of goods, prices, and who the goods were sold to. The measures reports & bills includes measures of the size and weight of goods on board ships.
  - Promissory Notes By Hicks, 1797-1808 (Box 81)
    This box contains 9 folders of promissory notes by Hicks from 1797-1808. These promissory notes are all for Hicks promising to pay various amounts of money to multiple individuals. It does not state what these payments are for.
  - Promissory Notes of Others, 1801-1803 (Box 82)
    This folder contains 2 folders of promissory notes undated, and from 1801-1803. Most of the promissory notes begin with "on demand I promise to pay". Most are to Isaac Hicks in case individuals do not proceed to sea.
  - Account Books (Box 83)
    This box includes account books created by Isaac Hicks. Many appear to be homemade, with covers made from newspaper, homemade paper, and other scrap paper. They appear to be for individual ships. Most are empty or close to empty and may only have a page or two filled. One book is a list of ships freight, and it is sorted in the book by first letter of the ship. Some books include bills payable and bills receivable. Another book is a copy of an act incorporating the Newark Banking and Insurance Company. One book is in French. Also included is a folder of notes that are a modern addition.
  - Duty, Undated (Box 84)
    This box includes 2 folders of undated material. Most of the documents are extremely difficult to read. Some of the documents are written on paper, while others appear to be written on parchment of some sort. It appears that these documents are for duties paid on goods.
  - Memorandum Books, 1790-1803 (Box 85)
    This box contains 16 folders of memorandum books. Each folder contains one book. Some are bound in leather, while others appear to be handmade and are bound in newspaper or handmade paper. Most memorandum books are account books. Some are for specific banks and individuals, and others are more general. Most books are not filled completely, and some only have a few pages with writing on them.
  - Memorandum Books & Bills of Parcels, 1798, 1804, 1809 (Box 86)
    This folder includes 10 folders. 4 folders are memorandum books and 6 folders are bills of parcels. Two folders of memorandum books includes an additional sheet of notepaper that has been added at a later date, which includes some notes regarding the book. The books are predominantly bound in leather. The bills of parcels are bills for (usually) individual goods. Some bills say where the goods are going to be shipped to, while others just include the goods and costs.
  - Deposition-Russel & Hathaway v. Barker; Samples of Fabric, 1791-1804 (Box 87)
    This box includes 3 folders. The first folder is simply the original wrapping for the deposition. The second folder includes a deposition for Asa Russel & Stephen Hathaway Jr, vs. Jacob Barker from 1802. The deposition includes questions executed on behalf of Edward Forbes. The topic has to do with John Deaves refusing to pay for goods cosigned to him because he believed the goods were injured in some way. The third folder includes small samples of fabrics, probably that Hicks would be interested in purchasing in bulk. Each sample is on an individual scrap of paper with a description of the fabric. Also included are two notes in French, that appear to be pricing lists for the fabric.
  - Miscellaneous Indentures, Receipts, Invoices, 1790-1805 (Box 88)
    This box includes 11 folders with assorted materials. It includes foreign correspondence, invoices, indentures, and other miscellaneous materials. These materials will not be re-inserted into their appropriate folders, and instead will remain in this box.
  - Charter Parties; Bills, 1794-1806 (Box 89)
    The bills are housed in long, narrow sheets, that have been bound together with twine. Most simply say 'paid x bill'. It appears that these might have been bound together into a larger book at some point, and may have had checks attached. The folder that contained materials regarding charter parties includes data about ships, where they were going, some of the goods they shipped, and costs for the voyage.
    Ships mentioned include Sarah, Columbia, Lucretia, Oswego, President, and Thomas
  - Estates of J&W Blackstone; John Gray, 1801-1804 (Box 104)
    This box contains three folders of materials regarding the estates of James and William Blackstone, & John Gray. The folders contain general business papers including ballance sheets, inventories, and legal documents regarding financial issues.
  - Hicks Waste Book, Feb 1795-Sept 1797 (Box 90)
    This book is labeled Waste Book. It is more than half empty. It looks almost like an account book, where one side of the page has notes, and the opposite side of the page has monetary values.
  - Hicks Daybook, 1791-1792 (Box 91)
    This book was a daybook used by Isaac Hicks when he was a part of Alsop and Hicks. This daybook was used by Hicks to record daily transactions with his business. The entries are ordered chronologically rather than by individual or ship name. It also appears that this book was used later for pressing leaves and flowers, and has the name 'Freddie Herbert Cocks' in the cover, as well as on some pages in a child's handwriting. The leaves and flowers have been removed from the pages and are included in mylar in the box.
  - Hicks Invoice Book, 1796-1807 (Box 92)
    This book includes copies of invoices of goods shipped by Hicks. It is unclear if these are copies of invoices found elsewhere in the collection. It also appears that there is some water damage to the top of the book, and the ink there is extremely faded. The book is approximately 2/3 full.
  - Hicks Account Book, 1801-1802 (Box 93)
    This book is a daily cash account book for Isaac Hicks. The materials are ordered chronologically, and the debits are primarily towards individuals rather than for materials or shipping needs.
  - Hicks (and Doughty) Account Book, 1795-1797 (Box 94)
    This book is a daily cash account book for Isaac Hicks when he was part of the partnership of Hicks and Doughty. The left page is debits and the right page is credits. These are ordered chronologically. Some pages are labeled Charles Doughty, Alsop & Hicks, Latham Bunker, William Ross, Adventure to Dublin, Adventure to France, and more.
  - Hicks Account Book, 1790-1819 (Box 95)
    This book is an account book for Isaac Hicks. It is organized chronologically, and includes names of individuals with whom Hicks worked with. On the left side of some pages are debits and on the right, credits. Some pressed leaves have been removed from the pages, and are included in mylar in the front of the box.
  - Hicks Invoice Book, 1792-1800 (Box 96)
    This book is titled "Alsop & Hicks Invoice Book". It includes copies of invoices of goods shipped by Hicks. It is unclear if these invoices are also elsewhere in the collection. The invoices are chronological within the book, and can include ships names, captains, ports left, destinations, lists of goods and pricing. Approximately 1/3 through the book appears to be an alphabetized index, listing names, and pages that those names will be found on.
  - Hicks Daybook, May 1796-Jan 1797 (Box 97)
    This volume is labeled "waste book" on the spine. It appears to have some water damage. It appears to be an account book, where Hicks records money going out, goods coming in, and names of clients.
  - Hicks Account Book, 1793-1800 (Box 98)
    This book is an account book used by Hicks. It includes debits and credits and is in a chronological order. The book is missing its cover, back, and most of its spine, but is still stitched together.
  - Hicks Account Book, 1799-1802 (Box 99)
    This book is a different sort of account book. Rather than being sorted by date, it is sorted by individual. Otherwise, the material is similar to the other account books in the collection.
  - Hicks Receipt Book, 1801 (Box 100)
    This book includes copies of receipts. The first page states "Isaac Hicks's receipt Book Commenced 1mth 31th 1801, Twenty Fifth Year of Independence, When peace is expected between France and American which will be happily received." The pages are filled with notes of materials and money received. It appears that these are in some sort of chronological order, though the receipts are not dated. They are also written and signed by different individuals. It is unclear if these receipts are duplicated in the collection.
  - Hicks Receipt Book, Undated (Box 101)
    This book includes copies of receipts. Inside the cover is a letter, apparently written after the time of the book, that briefly discusses the history of Alsop & Hicks, including goods sold, and the fact that their business ventures were subsiding in the dry goods business. Inside the back cover is a paper with a drawing of a boat and some mathematical formulas. Inside this paper are assorted receipts. The book is only approximately 1/3 full.
  - Hicks Bill Book, 1799-1805 (Box 102)